<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Præfestinantis morator, or, Mr. Tombs his præcursor, staid, examined, and proved not to be from Heaven, but of men.</title>
            <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74871</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50805967</idno>
  <idno type="VID">166114</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248532215</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E659_9</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">50805967</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74871)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166114)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 101:E659[9b])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Præfestinantis morator, or, Mr. Tombs his præcursor, staid, examined, and proved not to be from Heaven, but of men.</title>
                  <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
                  <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. Plain Scripture proof of infants church-membership and baptism.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2] p., p. 371-415.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Originally part of: Plain Scripture proof of infants church-membership and baptism / by Richard Baxter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
                  <note>With: A friendly accomodation in the fore-debated controversie between Mr. Bedford and the author. London : [s.n.], Printed, anno dom. 1652 -- Letters that passed between Mr. Baxter and Mr. Tombes concerning the dispute. London, : [s.n.], Printed in the year, 1652.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Tombes, John, 1603?-1676.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166114:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Praefestinantis Morator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, Mr. Tombs His <hi>PRAECVRSOR,</hi> Staid and Examined, and Proved not to be from HEAVEN, but of Man.</p>
            <p>Yet GOD by Mr. <hi>T.</hi> sendeth this Truth to the hearts of <hi>all whom it may concern.</hi> Praecurs. pag. 82, 83.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Pastors and Teachers, or Presbyters to Teach and Govern the Church of God, I am assured are a Divine Institution, and a very mercifull gift of Christ,</hi> Eph 4. 11, 12. 13. 1 Cor. 12. 28. Act. 14. 23. 1 Tim. 3. 1. Tit. 2. 5. <hi>to whom People should yield obedience,</hi> Heb. 13. 7. 17. <hi>and yield maintenance liberally,</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 14. Gal. 6. 6. 1 Tim. 5. 17, 18.</p>
            <p>If any go about to extirpate them, let him be accursed as an Enemy to Christ and his Church.]</p>
            <p>Or if <hi>Socinus</hi> be of more Authority with them, let them receive the same Truth from their <hi>Cracovian</hi> Catech. de Eccles. cap. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the year, 1652.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:166114:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="371" facs="tcp:166114:2"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>OF the Antiquity of Infant-Baptism.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of my allegation of <hi>Hyginus</hi> institution of Gossips.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Whether all Disciples should be baptized.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>T.</hi> untruly chargeth me with preaching against Anabaptists because I wrote against them.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect</hi> 7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I truly mentioned his plurality of places.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>T.</hi> his unworthy dealing with me about my Doctrine of the Nature of Faith.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Whether he excuse not sinners from the guilt of breaking their Baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Covenant.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Whether he accuse not his own children as no Christians.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Whether men are in Covenant <hi>eo nomine</hi> because elected.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Relation of a servant may be, where there is not service.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>My meaning fully opened, of the term <hi>[Visible]</hi> as to the Church or Members.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Whether I had not reason to think that Mr. <hi>T.</hi> judgeth it best for Infants not to be Christians.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A fuller explication of my meaning of Infant-Holiness, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Consequences of the Anabaptistical principle of not communicating with the (supposed) unbaptized.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gods admirable Providence in keeping the Orthodox from the notorious guilt of this Age, and leaving testimonies to vindicate them from the calumnies of all enemies.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gods eminent appearance by providence against the Anabaptists and other Sects of this age.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>T.</hi> his reasons for private mens administring Sacraments confuted; and those against it defended.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>His reasons against Magistrates tenure from the Redeemer confuted.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="372" facs="tcp:166114:3"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ancients and Modern, Orthodox Divines, took not Infant Baptism as without Scripture proof.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>How far Mr. <hi>T</hi> goes towards the overthrow of the Ministry.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>People are not to govern by Vote. The Elders have more to do then the people in Excommunication: Excommunication a part of Government.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>My mistake of the sense of <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 15, 16. acknowledged and corrected.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>T.</hi> doth dangerously extenuate, and speak dishonourably of Christs Kingdom.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Letters between Mr. <hi>T.</hi> and me about Writing and Disputing.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="373" facs="tcp:166114:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Reverend and unfeinedly beloved Brother (for so I will call you whether you will or no:) I lately overtook your <hi>Praecursor,</hi> and finding him in a publike and (too) common Road (though out of his way) I presently enquired after and perused his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence. (News pleaseth humane Nature; especially when it concerneth us.) I confess I had no high expectation of satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; but yet I looked for something new, after so great provocations and promises: But I found the old matter, the old stile, with the supplement of fourteen sheets of Paper, which had they been bare, had been worth three pence, and would have served me for some better use. A new Title also I confess I found: And its like no mock-Title (as you judged mine)<hi>—Festinans caecos parit—</hi>It makes more haste then good speed, so nimble footed as to overrun the Truth. The Proverb saith, <hi>The late Messenger brings the truest news.</hi> And a wiser concludes. <hi>He that is first in his own cause, seemeth just; but his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour cometh and searcheth him.</hi> Prov. 18. 17. <hi>John</hi> may out-run <hi>Peter,</hi> and go last into the Sepulcher.</p>
            <p>I have declared my intentions never to meddle with you more, while you continue <hi>Eandem canere Cantilenam;</hi> but I durst not tye my self, as having found God crossing my purposes by his providential Call. Two things now prevail with me to do what is here done. 1. That your <hi>Praecursor</hi> set forth at that very season when my Book is in the Press for a third Edition: 2. The advice of some friends to take this season, who otherwise would have had me to have confuted you with silence. Because men must an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer for every idle word and work, and every lost hour: I will say nothing to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated or frivilous passages in your papers (which is most) but in each Section touch on that which is most material or new. The Lord guide my Spirit and Pen, that I may do it in his fear, and light; and may not vent my own fancies or passions, nor let fall a word to the injury of his Truth.</p>
            <p>You divulge the great humility of the six Gentlemen, who will so patiently permit you to affix their names to such a paper. I know none of them but Major Gen. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison,</hi> whom I love so well that I wish he may patronize a better cause. I finde the old querulous strain in your Epistle, as if you were much desirous to be noted for a Sufferer. You first complain of [a new storm by the violence of men bent to bear down dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from the determinations of the Assembly, &amp;c.] This storm did bear you down from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Bewdely, Ross,</hi> &amp;c. I wish you less suffering or more patience. Your next suffering was, that you found not the settlement which you hoped for in the
<pb n="374" facs="tcp:166114:4"/> Countrey. I doubt those hopes are the root of your unsetledness. Two causes of this, you assign. 1. The States sold your Lands, out of which your maintenance there arose. Are not the Gentlemen you speak to, part of the State whom you accuse? But if it were your Lands, the fault was the less: some said, it was the Churches and some said it was Gods. 2. You say, the alienating of mens spirits from you through the distance between you and the Antagonist, did in agreat measure frustrate your hopes. God useth to frustrate hopes of settlement on earth. I am glad you can charge the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagonist with nothing but distance (and that only in judgment, not in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.)</p>
            <p>Your second Epistle is querulous too, that [you finde neither your Antidote, nor your speech regarded by many, nor perhaps will this writing take much with them.] You might easily foretell that by the quality of your work; except with those chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that every wind of Doctrine will toss to and fro. But let's see what the book it self will afford, to that discovery of my injuriousness and weakness which you say [will appear in part by reading it.]</p>
            <p>To what end you recite my Allegation of <hi>Just. Martyr,</hi> is past my reach to imagine: Vnless you would insinuate that I confess this to be the course with all <hi>the baptized, which I expresly say was the way of baptizing the aged.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. 1.</head>
               <p>To your first Section I have nothing to say.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <p>To the second but little; for it needs not. The supposed contradiction in my words, had been removed, had it pleased you to read or cite them all, in <hi>pag.</hi> 9. And is it a contradiction to say, <hi>[The gate is strait, the way narrow]</hi> and yet <hi>[his yoke is easie, his burden light, and his commands not grievous?]</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <p>The sum of your Answers to the words of the Ancients, seems to me to be this [I will regard nothing that Antiquity saith against my opinion.] Such is your Answer to <hi>Origen.</hi> It is not in one or two places only that he speaks for Infant-baptism, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the less likely to be corrupted. <hi>Augustines</hi> rule you cite by the halfs leaving out [and was not instituted by Councels, but hath been ever held.) Your cross instances seem vain. 1. Episcopacie no doubt is of Apostolical Ordination; but if you mean Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>san Episcopacy, it is so far from having <hi>Austins</hi> universal Antiquity, that the first Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters manifest they then knew it not. 2. The time of <hi>Easter</hi> as it was at first a matter of no great observation to Christians, &amp; therefore might well be forgotten, as was the time of Christs Nativity, so it never pretended to universal consent, one part of the Church pleading for one time, and others for another. 3. Infant Communion is not once mentioned till many 100 years after <hi>Christ;</hi> but enough against it in the first Writers. 4. The Millenaries opinion, was only affirmed to come from <hi>John</hi> by some particular men; and it is not matter of Fact, but of Doctrine, wherein Tradition hath less Authority. But are any of these like to the matter of Baptizing Infants, which must needs be so notorious, that it is next to impossible, that <hi>Origen, Cyprian</hi> and the Church in their times should be ignorant whether this had been the former Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches practise. Matters of Fact themselves are very different: some practised, but once or long before, or in a corner: some often even through all the Churches, and ordinarily. This in question is of the latter sort. If indeed you think that <hi>Austins</hi> Rule is uncertain in such matters as these, I desire you by the next to tell me, how
<pb n="375" facs="tcp:166114:4"/> you know whether the Scriptures which you now use are the same Books in whole or part which were extant in the Apostles age, and that there was not more, and which be Canonical, &amp;c. Do not you care to smite through Christianity, so you may bring down Infant-Baptism? <hi>Salmasius</hi> and some others speak as rashly and partially as you. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you deny nothing in <hi>Justin Martyrs</hi> words, you must yield that it was known then to mothers that their Infants were of Gods Kingdom, and then certainly they were Church members and known Disciples or Christians; for none but Christians are known to be of Gods Kingdom. And all Christians are Disciples, <hi>Act.</hi> 11. 26. and all Disciples must be baptized, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. You think <hi>Cyprian</hi> and all the Councel (and consequently all their Church) might be ignorant whether Infants were baptized 100 years before. And why? Because [it was not at all or very rarely] A rare Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment! if it were [not at all] why might they not know that? You say, They might not know that Infants were not baptized, because they were not baptized; that is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it were cognoscible. It may be the same is your reason on the other side, They might be ignorant that they were baptized, because they were. But why should you think it rarely done? (If so, yet it was done) Doubtless either the Apostles used and appointed it ordinarily, or not at all. 2. You say, it is not known of what age those 66. Bishops were; a perplexing doubt! You may be sure All or some were Seniors; and its like if never a one of them were old. yet they had old men of their Churches; unless you le say, It is possible that no old men were Christians. I am sure its not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable. 3. You say, its not known whose children they were. But as its most probable that some of them were Christians children, so its certain that the children of former Christians were then Christians among them, either Pastors or Members, or both, and that in great numbers. And for what the Epistle expresseth and implyeth of the Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I am content it self be judge. Sure I am, it makes no question of Infant-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, nor did <hi>Fidus</hi> whom they answer. I think you were guided to translate the Epistle to the confutation of your self. But your great noise is about <hi>Hyginus</hi> making Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sips: where 1. you feign me to triumph in it, that so you might be thought to have done something in confuting it. But I lay so little stress on it, that I think it not of such moment as you intimate. 2. You fall again to the old way in two Answers. 1. You say [the Decree in the Epistle, &amp;c. mentioneth not Infant baptism though it speaks of Gossips, &amp;c. <hi>Reply</hi> 1. It is utterly untrue that the Epistles have one word of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree or of Gossips: I have not <hi>Osiander</hi> at hand; but if he do speak so falsly as you say, I will less believe him hereafter; if he do not, you are the less to be believed. 2. You have satisfied me hereby that you never read the Epistles, which yet you might have done in so many Authors: why then would you be so rash as to misreport them, without first consulting them. Neither <hi>Blondellus, Surius, Nicolinus, Crab, Binius, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> nor any other that ever I read, have any more Epistles of <hi>Hyginus</hi> but two; nel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which have one word of any such business. 2 You tell me of divers Writers that so disprove the Epistles, that you could hardly have imagined any harmed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant would ever have thus alledged so notoriously forged a writing] and you tell me [I have reason to be ashamed of abusing men with this forgery after so much eviction of it by learned men, being more like to a brazen faced allegation, &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> What man that reads these words would imagine that all this were false, and meerly forged out of your own brain? Yet so it is. How could you think to perswade any knowing Reader that this is true, who hath my Book to see its all your fiction. Do I not know that the Decree of <hi>Hyginus</hi> is not in his Epistles at all? but mentioned by themselves by <hi>Gratian,</hi> as received by Historical Tradition, and not at all on the credit of those Epistles? Did I not expresly therefore tell you that I took it on the
<pb n="376" facs="tcp:166114:5"/> consent of History? Did I once mention the Epistles at all? Let any judge that reads my Book. Why would you forge all this without one word to occasion you? Do you think the deceiving of the simple is the winning of your Cause? I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant what your cited Authors say against the Epistles (whether solidly against all, as well as some, I judge not) and divers more (especially <hi>Blondellus)</hi> that say much more then <hi>Reynolds.</hi> Whether the Tradition that I alledge be currant, I leave men to judge as they see cause: But certainly you venture far to charge me with these things concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Epistles. For what you say about interpretation of Scripture, I easier believe my skil to be small, then yours to be great: at least where prejudice perverteth your understanding. Let your next words stand as witness, where you so confidently li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit so many generals; and think your poor reasons prove that Christ there invites men to him only as a Teacher, (and consequently only such as are weary of other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine) and not those that are weary of sin; and teacheth them not meekness by his example, but only by his Doctrine: <hi>And you think by proving one, you disprove the other, as if they were opposite.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <p>The next deserves no Reply, being such discernably gross evasions; specially that plain contradiction about <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 10. For his zeal to promote his opinion, and his actuall withdrawing men into other bodies, let his hearers, and all that know his way judge. None that know him I think will believe what he saith of this, but his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <p>I have thanked you for your exceptions against some points in my <hi>Aphorisms;</hi> but you might have also acknowledged that you received a Reply; even 12 sheets to your one leaf and side. It seems to me an unworthy act to publish all these reproachfull ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusations against master <hi>Boraston,</hi> who never medled with you in that way. Would it not sufficiently ease your stomack that you might have your full stroak at me? But whoever stands in your way must taste of your spleen. Will any man think your accusation should be received, that hath not heard what he can say for himself? I think it needless to tell the word what I have heard him say to these Charges of yours: but this I will say, that if by [temporizing with the Kings partie] you mean [staying at home] so did most of the godliest in <hi>Bewdley,</hi> and thanked God they might: But if you mean, either that he was for them, or did not in preaching reprove them (which yet was then dangerous) master <hi>William Hopkins,</hi> now with God, did seriously to me profess the contrary, and vindicate him in both these particulars. The Magistrate also must be censured with the rest; yea, and the others that invited me (though as eminent for parts and piety as any I know there) must be said to be [of somewhat a like stamp] whereby it appears of what validity are your Accusations, and how you will stamp all that are against your Anabaptism.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. 6.</head>
               <p>I am the more obliged to observe what you say in this Section, because you say it is to the chief points in my Book: And therefore I may perceive here what way you mean to go in your larger Answer: and perhaps the Reply to this may suffice to the sum of that.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You say, your confession that all should be admitted Church-members by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, was meant of such as by their profession are visible, not of such as are visible in my way without profession.</p>
               <pb n="377" facs="tcp:166114:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> But how oft did you confess it of All in general? But I thought how slippery you were! And yet for all this you dare not say yet that Christ hath any Disciples that (ordinarily) ought not to be admitted by Baptism. But the best is, even that which you yielded was proved. Christ will have no Disciples enter at any other door, ordinarily <hi>[Go, disciple me all nations, baptizing them.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. You say, As yet you finde no Law or Ordinance (for Infants Visible Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membership) save what is enjoyned concerning Circumcision.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> What not yet? And yet dare you boast so confidently of your prepared con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation? Yet can you finde no Law that made Women Church-members? nor the uncircumcised Males in the Wilderness! O the power of prejudice!</p>
               <p n="3">3. You say, you answer my challenge by another challenge; To shew what one Church had Infants Visible Church-members besides the Jews.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. The Church in <hi>Abrahams</hi> family, who were no <hi>Jews.</hi> 2. My Books answers you as to others. 3. And I answer your Challenge with another Challenge, to shew me what one Visible Church on earth besides the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> we have any such History of, as from whence we may expect any light concerning that Case? when even multitudes of Divines acknowledge not the being of any other visible Church; yet consequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial proofs I have given him already. To my second demand [What one man denyed Infants Church-membership till within this two hundred years?] He answers, not by naming any one.</p>
               <p>But 1. he saith, Till <hi>Abrahams</hi> time nothing is said about any Church frame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> But as God had his Church till then; so I have proved Gods love the same to his Peoples seed, and that the second Commandment as to its promise was Moral, and that Infants Church-membership begun not with Circumcision. The rest of his Answer I think not worth the taking notice of.</p>
               <p>He saith [Infants are excluded from Baptism by <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. 15, 16.] As if it were excluding part of Disciples, and part of Nations, for Christ to command them <hi>[to disciple all nations baptizing them?]</hi> He returns a question [What great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort follows this, that our Infants are by Nature the children of wrath?]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. It is a point beyond controversie, in plain discovery. Is this so? 2. Take heed of equalling your own opinions to Gods clear Truths. 3. It is a point of great necessity to be known, and tends to this consolation; that [else Infants could not be saved by Christ] which now they are. Next he falls on another passage of mine, that [To be visibly in or out of the Church, is all one as visibly (or to our judgment) to belong or not belong to Christ and Heaven.] This he denyes, and doubts not to shew that this mistake hath much mislead me; and saith, he can prove that Christ will save his Elect though no Christians in appearance, nor Disciples by profession, nor visible Subjects of his Kingdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. But whats that to the question? Because he will save an undiscernable Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, that dyeth he can make profession of his Faith; doth it therefore follow that he that is so saved was visibly a Church member? or that to be visibly in or out of the Church, is not to be visibly or probably in or out of Christs true Kingdom? Can you have any knowledge who they be whom Christ will save, that are not visibly Church-members? 2. I advise you to take heed of asserting the Salvation of any meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as Elect. They must be in Covenant or under the promise, as well as Elect; or else you know nothing of their salvation. And who are under such a promise, besides Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians or Church members? The rest of this Section sweet and sour, shall pass as it is for me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="378" facs="tcp:166114:6"/>
               <head>§. 7.</head>
               <p>To all this Section I will say little; only Mr. <hi>T.</hi> denyeth not the Truth of my Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in any material point. Only where I said, I never spoke against his opinion; he saith, My memory retains not all I printed, &amp;c. and cites a word <hi>(pag.</hi> 534. of my Book of Rest.) But Mr. <hi>T.</hi> untruly intimates that those words were preached; for they never were; nor twenty and twenty leaves in that book besides. But I still see weak grounds will serve his turn. I see also he is too tender of his credit when he professeth to have done what he did this way on <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. that he might stand right in one mans thoughts. I advise him to preach to better ends, or else no wonder if he preach no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doctrine. It is hard preaching Christ and your self together. I am sorry the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents Cause is so low with you, that you have yet no way to excuse them from being Hereticks, but [that its unknown to you that they make a party for their Error.] Your charity is greater or your knowledge less then they seem; then no wonder if you know not harder matters. I doubt its known at <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Constantinople,</hi> which yet you cannot know here. You do not know that you make a party your self, neither its like! Well! I wish these men to consider where you leave them, and look out for a better defence then this: Lastly, you did confirm what I did surmise: for you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not but that your design in desiring my Animadversions was to put them with the rest into your review: And so now I perceive what would come on it, if I had yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to your desires.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>§. 8.</head>
               <p>You complain of the charge of Printing; for which I confess I am not much sorry, and do less compassionate you then for any other of your calamities. But I must tell you it is long of your self. When you put forth such Books as this, would you be so uncharitable as to wish poor men to part with their money to buy them, and time to read them? If the weekly Pamphlets did sing nothing but the same song, who would buy them? But I finde by the last Weeks News book (of <hi>August</hi> 31) that you have found out a cheaper way of writing: And I confess I applaud it, and think it had been better that your <hi>Praecursor</hi> had gone Post by the same way: Only (though by your oft mentioning me so publickly. I perceive that I have a room in your thoughts) I was sorry there to finde, 1. That I was any occasion of the <hi>Oxford</hi> Challenge. 2. And that you ventured to pass your judgement so far on such men and so many, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that you <hi>[saw little of Gods Spirit in their Intentions and ways.]</hi> But the angring passage was about your Revenues: where you say, I would have the world believe it was desirable for my self. True or false, you venture to say so. Is reproving your Pluralities a sign of desiring them? Let me but tell you that if I had desired more, I could have had it; yea, was offered 500 <hi>per annum</hi> without Plurality. I pray you be not jealous of my desiring your Revenues; for I do not think ever a neighbour you have will tell you that you need to fear me. I am loth to talk of these matters. Where you say, I was unplundered, I say, <hi>Cantabit vacuus,</hi> I had nothing to lose, but Books and a Horse, which were lost, but that part of my books were preserved; and I never sought or received reparations, but served the State much of my time for nothing. And where you tell me of a good estate in Land that I am heir to, I must tell you, I am never the richer for that, nor desire ever to be. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Sir, my 100. l. <hi>per annum</hi> is much more (for all my very chargeable weakness) then I know what to do with for my self. And had I not better ways to expend some of it,
<pb n="379" facs="tcp:166114:6"/> I should desire to rid my hands of it well: but you say [It is false and exceeding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to you] that I say, [you had four Market Towns on your shoulders,] and yet complain, &amp;c. Is this false? 1. You say, [There are no words that have a shew of complaint, but those in the close of your <hi>Examen</hi> and <hi>Apology.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. Two is enough. 2. Let the impartial Reader peruse the Epistle to your Antidote, and judge whether this be true. 3. Even this book must yet speak the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the rest, and in the Dedication complain of a storm from the violence of men bent to bear down Dissenters from the determinations of the Assembly &amp;c. the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of your hopes by the States selling your lands, &amp;c. But what need I look fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when even here where you deny it, you say [I cannot but be sensible of the great wrong I receive in my name, and perhaps in my estate by Mr. <hi>B.</hi> his calumnies.] I am sorry you cannot but be sensible, even when its but a [perhaps:] And such a [perhaps] as could be conceived by nothing but distempered jealousie: and jealousie comes from too much love. Never fear it, Sir, I promise you, I will not diminish your estate a farthing, if I can help it. This Terrene Melancholy makes you too sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible. I do not think all your neighbours you have, can conjecture which way I may wrong you in your estate; except only in the sale of your Books: and I hope you mean not that. This is my first untruth: whats the second? I cannot gather it out of all your Narration, except that be it in the first words [that I had four Market Towns on my shoulders; which every one will interpret to be four beneficial Places under my charge together.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply</hi> 1. And can mens interpretations make my true words false? 2. Did not I tell you to your face, that it was the Plurality that I excepted against, more then the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit? 3. Let me ask you these two or three questions. 1. Were you not at once, even when I wrote those words, Preacher Resident at <hi>Bewdley,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Lempster,</hi> Parson of <hi>Ross,</hi> Master of the Hospital at <hi>Ledbury?</hi> You will not sure deny it? 2. Had you not three of these long before that? 3. Could I foreknow then how soon you would (willing or unwilling) leave <hi>Ross</hi> or <hi>Bewdley?</hi> 4. Were not all these Market Towns? 5. Is there any doubt whether they were all beneficial to you, except <hi>Lempster?</hi> And 6. did you not long hold the title of that, to the keeping out of any other? And was it not all the Ecclesiastical means you had heretofore? (though I believe you received not much from the destitute people.) And did I not tell you that a reverend Minister told me that they offered you 60. l. to quit your title, that they might put in another, and you would not? and you did not deny it? 7. Ought you to take publique main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for nothing? Or were you sufficient for all these places? I dare say confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that you have as much to do at <hi>Lempster</hi> as you and such another is able to do. 8. Doth not the Hospital at <hi>Ledbury</hi> bind you to about four moneths residence yearly? And can you be four moneths conscionably absent from your charge? But I doubt your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion will salve this, and you will take none but the Rebaptized for your proper charge. Where now is the untruth? And how seriously have I heard you complain against that godly Knight, in the very words here used by you pag. 25. line last [so great was the Antipathy of some men against me, that I could neither get reparations for my losses, nor allowance for building, nor augmentation &amp;c.] I am forced to speak these (otherwise inconvenient) passages, because you charge me with untruth. As for the Assembly of Divines whom you mention, I think you would not have had them disobey the Parliament that called them to that service: nor yet to have forborn to preach ordinarily in <hi>London:</hi> (if they had, they might well have been accused:) Nor yet to give up their Pastoral charges in the Country, because they were detained on a temporary service, no more then Chaplains in the Army should give up theirs.</p>
               <pb n="380" facs="tcp:166114:7"/>
               <p> But I must needs tell you, that you go on in mistakes, when you say, that [had you been an Assembly man, you might have been stiled in my Books a Learned, Holy, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental, Judicious, Humble, Heart-piercing Preacher.] I honour your worth; but had you been an Archbishop or Cardinal, or had you been President of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, I think I should have given you no such titles, without knowing more by you then yet I do. It seems you think your self as worthy of it, as those to whom I gave it; But I confess I never so thought. Must others prize you as highly as you prize your self? For the prophane passages you mention, I say, I never thought Christ spoke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanely in saying, <hi>They that kill you shall think they do God service:</hi> Nor to tell the Pharisees, <hi>Wo to you Hypocrites, &amp;c. Your fathers killed the Prophets, and ye build their Sepulchres, &amp;c.</hi> Nor for the Prophet to tell men, <hi>That they sacrificed to their own nets;</hi> Nor for God to say to the wicked, <hi>Thou thoughtest I was altogether such a one as thy self.</hi> Or for <hi>Elias</hi> to say, <hi>Cry aloud, for he is a God; either he is talking or pursuing, or he is in a journey.</hi> Or for <hi>Paul</hi> to say, <hi>Beware of dogs, beware of the Concision;</hi> no nor <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruks</hi> description of Idols.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>§. 9.</head>
               <p>For what is said of the business of the <hi>Waldenses,</hi> I think it not worth the labour to say any more then is said, or to discover the additional slips of this Paper; nor yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his charge against my Doctrine of Justification, but only this. Let the Reader ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve <hi>Mr. T.</hi> his ingenuous dealing. 1. He chargeth me with these words in my book of Rest [Doubtless the Gospel takes Faith for all Gospel precepts] and addeth his own Commentary in the same distinct character, as if they were my words. 2. These words he accused in his Animadversions on my Aphorisms; to which I replyed in these words [In that <hi>pag.</hi> 11. I apprehended my self so obvious to misconstruction, that I have corrected it in the second Edition, which is now Printed: Yet 1. I speak not of Faith as justifying, but as the condition of Salvation, which contains more then that which is the condition of our first Justification. 2. I never termed those [Gospel precepts] which are not in some way proper to the Gospel.] Hereupon Mr. <hi>T.</hi> sent to me for the second Edition of my book of Rest, wherein all this was altered: He never made me any Reply to this. Yet doth he so long after charge on me those same words which I told him I had revoked, and that in the sense contrary to the words themselves, and my explication to him. He speaks here of sending his exceptions, but nothing of his never returning any thing to my Reply. In which Reply I answered the four exceptions here mentioned pag. 32. Nay whereas he maketh this my fourth Errour [my making obedience to all Gospel precepts an essential part of Justifying Faith] Let the Reader note, 1. It is utterly untrue: I never wrote such a word: He puts in [Obedience] for [Subjection to Christ] and [justifying Faith] for saving Faith. 2. Yea this same thing he charged on me in his Animadversions, and brought many Arguments against it: and I largely shewed him his mistakes; that by [sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to Christ] I meant the Covenanting or consenting to be at first his subjects; which stateth the relation, and is not strictly obedience to Christ, but prerequisite; Even as contracting or consenting that such a man be my Soveraign, my Master, Teacher, &amp;c. goes before actually obeying him: and the form of obedience presup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth the said Relation. Yet doth Mr. <hi>T.</hi> after all this deliberately again charge me with the same words, which I shewed 1. that I never wrote, 2. nor ever thought, nor intended his sence. Other foul passages here I will pass.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="381" facs="tcp:166114:7"/>
               <head>§. 10.</head>
               <p>Again, you go on a very falshood in vindicating your Informers; as if I preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the words which you mention in my book of Rest, against Anabaptists; which is untrue. Whether you forced me to dispute, shall more appear by your Letters. <hi>Pag▪</hi> 34. Mr. <hi>T.</hi> saith it is my fiction that telleth sinners that they never sinned against their Baptism and Engagement. <hi>Reply,</hi> 1. I desire the Reader to peruse my words <hi>pag.</hi> 174. 2. Let any impartiall man judge, Whether that man do not wholly excuse sinners from being guilty of violating their baptismall Engagement, (and so teach them that they need not repent of it, nor seek to Christ for pardon of it) who teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them that they never were baptized, or by Baptism engaged to God? Can he break a Covenant that was not bound by Covenant?</p>
               <p>To prove Mr. <hi>T.</hi> an accuser of his own children, I shewed <hi>pag.</hi> 175. that there is a double accusation; the one when men are charged with the <hi>reatus culpae:</hi> the other when they are charged with the <hi>reatus poenae,</hi> or to be <hi>obligati ad poenam:</hi> And I shewed that this is Satans end in charging the former: This is the principall Guilt intended by the Accuser; and he therefore proveth us guilty of the sin, that he may prove us obnoxious to the punishment: and therefore accusation is not only the charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a fault, as Mr. <hi>T.</hi> imagined. Here he hath nothing to say, but such words as I am loth to give their due Epithites to. He saith I discourse from the end of the Accuser and the opposition of Iustification to accusation and condemnation,] and that by the same reason the accusers accusation may be said to be condemnation and execution too, for that is the end of the accuser.] <hi>Reply,</hi> Strange Law and Logick! 1. All feigned, and made on your fingers ends. It was <hi>à materiâ,</hi> and not <hi>à fine,</hi> and the opposition of Justification to Condemnation, that I argued. I desire the Reader to peruse the place. 2. Every word of illustration in the whole page is not part of the Argument. 3. Do you not know that the end enters the Definition of these Relative morall Actions? Yet you say, [I had thought accusation noted the accusers act, not his end.] It seems then you are Ignorant that it denoteth <hi>actum moralem, qui à fine specificatur;</hi> both his act and his end! I perceive there are some obvious and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon truths that you yet know not. 4. And could you think (if I had argued from the end) that it would follow that accusation is condemnation and execution? Have these the same nearest end with accusation? It is the nearest end that specifies: the remote ends may be the same; but the next are not. He adds [that Justification is opposed to Accusation, and Condemnation shews they are distinguished, the one being the charging with a fault, the other passing sentence.] <hi>Reply.</hi> No doubt they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguished. But that accusation is only the charging of the <hi>reatum culpae,</hi> and not of the <hi>reatum poenae,</hi> is the thing that you should manifest. And let me now argue from the opposition of Justification to Accusation, though I did only use it for illustration before.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>reatus poenae</hi> charged on us unjustly, be <hi>terminus à quo</hi> of Iustification, then it may be the matter of accusation: But the antecedent is true: <hi>ergo, &amp;c.</hi> He addeth [I must confess I yet understand not his language of accusing without charging with a fault, nor do I think any Law▪dictionarie doth so define Accusation.] <hi>Reply,</hi> 1. But our question is, Whether accusation be any thing Besides or Distinct from the charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a fault? though not without it. 2. The fault here is taken <hi>pro confesso,</hi> and therefore needs no charge: Who knows not that all children have originall sin? (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept most Anabaptists and such like.) But it is only the <hi>debitum poenae,</hi> that is in
<pb n="382" facs="tcp:166114:8"/> question. 3. The Law knows no accusing a man to be <hi>obligatum ad poenam</hi> without charging with a fault: because it supposeth men to be reasonable; or at least the Law to be so reasonable as to admit no other accusation of that sort: But what shall we then think of them that are so unreasonable, as to accuse one as obnoxious to so great a suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, without accusing them of sin? 4▪ The English word [accusation] is used for the two Latine words <hi>[actio &amp; accusatio.]</hi> 5. Though usually <hi>actio</hi> is used in civils, and <hi>accusatio</hi> appropriated to criminals, yet are they also promiscuously used. I need not trouble Mr. <hi>T.</hi> with Dictionaries. Let him read <hi>Wesenbechius, Digest. Lib.</hi> 48. <hi>de Accusat. Tit.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 340. where he saith, <hi>Accusare etsi generaliter significat aliquem ad Causam dicendam urgere, unde Accusationis nomine etiam Civilis Actio &amp; persccutìo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, sicuti contra actio pro accusatione ponitur: tamen obtinuit, &amp;c.</hi> And sure you know that <hi>Actor</hi> doth Declare and Plead against <hi>Jus Possessionis, Jus Dominii, usus, &amp;c.</hi> Besides <hi>Delatio</hi> is in English a true Accusation, though not that publick one to which use hath commonly affixed that name. See also the same <hi>Wesenbech. in Cod. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 43. <hi>pag.</hi> 77. <hi>Accusatio autem ab Actione differt, quamvis in hac materia passim &amp; promiscue, alias Accusatio appellatur, alias vero Actio, &amp;c. Quamvis etiam haec qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damtenus est Accusatio, &amp;c. Et haec propria nota est qua Actiones ab Accusationibus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguuntur, quod in illis petitur aliquid ab Agente, in his vero Actor sibi nihil postulet, sed aut poenam fisco applicari aut reo infligi petat.</hi> And do not you desire the inflicting of this sad exclusion from the visible Church Covenant, &amp;c? yet still remember that it is your intending the Poenall Matter only that I charged you with, and not the form of a Poenalty.</p>
               <p>For his question about Janizaries or other Infidels, baptized in Infancie; Do I need to tell him again, That Apostates cease to be Church-members? and that the Infant Title will not serve those that disclaim Christ when they come to Age? and that the aged must have a title on personall Covenanting or Faith?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 35. he affirmeth me to say [that it is no more thanks to him then to Satan that he keeps not God from making promises to his children, <hi>p.</hi> 178.] when there is neither the words nor sense there. Only when he saith [I did never dispute them out of the Covenant] I said, no thanks to him, and I said, after, [Satan may say the like.] Is this to say, [Its no more thanks to him, then Satan, that he keeps not God from, &amp;c?] Yet doth he exclaim of this as beyond all moderation, when he maketh it himself. Doth he think no man will try his accusations by reveiwing my words?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 36. he chargeth me with [a most false speech] as he calls it, <hi>viz.</hi> [Nor are they in Covenant because elected.] <hi>Reply,</hi> Who will not easily understand these words, <hi>de Causa formali: q. d. eo nomine,</hi> because elected? And so he confesseth before, Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not a Covenant. Nor do I believe his interpretation of <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 8. that [the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of promise] is all one with [the Elect] if he mean it <hi>formaliter,</hi> and not only <hi>materialiter.</hi> But if my speech be most false, at least it will follow <hi>[electus est: ergo, foederatus est,]</hi> He is elect, therefore in Covenant. But that is falser then my speech. <hi>Adam</hi> and all the elect were elect from eternity; but were not so in Covenant. And the Covenant that now belongs to the elect before Conversion or faith (of themselves or parents) is not a mutuall Covenant, nor such as we treat of, and Baptism sealeth; But such as leaves them yet children of wrath, and hated of God. And doth <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. speak of that? It is the elect as Believers, and not as elect, (and therefore not till Believers) that are in the proper Covenant which we speak of. Then he citeth <hi>Ruther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> and <hi>Norton,</hi> saying <hi>soli electi foederati;</hi> as if that were all one with <hi>Omnes Electi!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He tels me of my confusion about the Covenants, and when he hath done, Distinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opens it in my words, as mine. He saith as if the Conditional Covenant is aequall
<pb n="383" facs="tcp:166114:8"/> to all till the Condition be performed; <hi>ergo,</hi> infants not believing, &amp;c. <hi>Reply.</hi> As if he knew not, that we maintain the Parents Faith, or accepting the Covenant for himself and his children to be the Infant condition? How forgetfull is Mr. <hi>T?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He saith, my saying in generall terms, that he denyeth that God covenanteth with Infants of believers to be their God in Christ, and to take them to be his peculiar people [is said like a Calumniator, his words being so plain to the contrary in that very place.] <hi>Reply, Quis teneat Proteum—?</hi> 1. [Infants of believers] are his words added to mine. It is Infants of Believers as such, and therefore al such that we are speaking of. 2. He saith, [Infants may have an interest in the Covenant of Christ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing elected; but whether they have or not, he cannot tell.] But 1. This is but some Infants, even the elect. 2. If he know not whether they have or not, then he thinks it not revealed in the word; and so he denies the Being in Covenant to some, and the knowledge as of all or any? Did I calumniate then in these words?</p>
               <p>But I desire Mr. <hi>Ts.</hi> followers to remember, that he here saith, that he there per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded not parents from engageing their children in Covenant, and promising in their names: I hope then they will do this much, if they will not baptize them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 39. There's a longer insulting over a supposed [monstrous absurditie, non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sense, gibberish;] then I will transcribe, but I will only tell him; 1. The relation of a servant in our case, is founded in Gods Dominion-Title, and as it is a Beneficiall Relation, supposeth our consent or our parents for us, as the <hi>conditio sine qua non.</hi> 2. The <hi>Terminus proximus</hi> is not service, actuall or intentionall, but <hi>Dominus</hi> the Correlate: <hi>servus est Domini servus.</hi> 3. The more remote <hi>Terminus</hi> of it, is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. 1. As it is a Relation of Duty, Duty is that <hi>Terminus,</hi> but it is Duty as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to, and not as in present Actuall existence: that actuall duty being yet a more remote term. A wife may be in that relation long before actuall procreation: you may bind an Infant as a servant. So do we, promising actuall obedience when he is capable; yet the Covenant begins the Relation without it. 2. As it is a Relation Beneficiall having right to the Priviledges of Gods family and Master-ship, so this Right is its <hi>Terminus:</hi> And this God is pleased to convey presently: he being capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of performing his promise, and the Infant capable of those benefits in great part, before the said Infant is capable of actuall obeying. Even as an Infant that hath his life in a Lease, and is bound to do homage or actuall service for it, when he is at age, is stated in the relation of a Tenant, and hath present right to the Land, though not presently capable of doing service. It is sufficient that this service as Due, have a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Being, and an <hi>esse cognitum,</hi> a thing engaged to be done when capable, though it have no present existence. So far the actuall existence of service is accidentall to the Being of the Relation, that it is seperable from it. Read but what I said, and now say, and review that insulting page of Mr. <hi>T.</hi> and if your observation meet not mine, that, [He usually is most confident, where he is most notoriously weak,] then you see not as I. If those triumphant passages shew not this learned man to be ignorant of the nature of Relations, then I cannot interpret them. Is it so strange to make an Infant a subject, and member of a Common wealth, before he can obey the Laws? They are <hi>membra imperfecta sed non imperfecte:</hi> at least <hi>verè membra, &amp; non tantum secundum quid.</hi> Doth he think when one had covenanted for so much with <hi>Aristotle</hi> to teach him, that he was not his Disciple before he learned of him. He saith, [It is monstrous absurditie to make a denomination without the form denominating, yea to count it accidentall to conceive a Relation without the foundation, which is all one as to call one a Father without begetting, a Lord without dominion, a sign without a significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.] and then he comes in with his merry riddle. <hi>Reply.</hi> But I would ask him 1. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="384" facs="tcp:166114:9"/> he be sure that the Denomination in a Relation, be taken only and ever from the foundation? 2. Whether he indeed did think when he wrote this, that actuall service is the <hi>fundamentum</hi> of the Relation of a servant? If he did—. If not—. 3. Whether actuall service have the same place in the Definition of the Relation of a servant, as Begetting in the Relation of a father. 4 Whether Dominion be the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Relation of a Lord, or rather the Form? 5. Doth he not confound the form, the <hi>Fundamentum</hi> and <hi>Terminus,</hi> as if they were all one, or I denyed all? I tell him therefore again, that (though he cal this <hi>absurdorum absurdissimum,</hi> which I should be ashamed of) that actuall service in existence is separable from a servant, perhaps while he lives: But I have stayed too long on this. The rest I pass.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>§. 11.</head>
               <p>This 11. §. hath nothing in it that I can find, which is not fully answered already. If the Reader will peruse my words and Mr. <hi>Ts.</hi> together, I desire no more: If he will not, I will not repeat the same things. Only I cannot but observe that Mr. <hi>T.</hi> seems <hi>pag.</hi> 42. to have a design to make the Reader believe that I use the word [Visible] in some odde sense, yea, and lay so great a stress on it, that when he hath shewed the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitness of that use, he hath overthrown all. And what is it? why [I mistake the term [Visible] as if it were as much as to appear such in the judgment of probability, though not discerned by sense, by which Definition the opposite terms Visible and Invisible, may be confounded, add the term Visible is used contrary, to the common use of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp;c.] <hi>Repl.</hi> I must the rather open the mysterious deceit of these words, because it seems he means to make some great matter of this, in his following book. 1. The word [such] is put ambiguously. If it relate to [the Visible Church membership] then it is a feigned absurditie. I hope he will not perswade men that I say [A Visible member is one that seems a Visible member.] If it relate to the term [Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber] undistinguished, then it is his fiction still. For I say not thus [A Visible mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is one that seems to be a member,] whether he be one or not. But if it relate to a Reall member of the mysticall body, then it is my sense, which I own: For in the place he mentioneth <hi>chap.</hi> 27. I distinguish of the word Church, into its Primary and its borrowed secondary sense. In the first it signifieth only the body mysticall of Christ: In the second it signifieth All that are engaged by Covenant to him; because they seem to be sincere, and of the mysticall body. So that I say, he that is so engaged by Covenant, doth more then seem to be a member of the Church, in the second sense of the word, <hi>viz.</hi> as it is called Visible: But he doth but seem <hi>(qua talis</hi> to us) to be of the mystica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Church, or of the Church in the first sense. (For mark that I divide not the <hi>genus</hi> into its <hi>species, sed aequivocum in sua aequivocata.)</hi> And I adde that the reason of the Appellation given to the Visible body, is its seeming to be the same with the mysticall: or that the name is given seconda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ily, borrowedly, from the mysticall to the visible. So that if you ask me, Whether it be certain or only probable, that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are members of the visible Church? I say, Certain. If you ask me, What is it that Directly or Immediately constituteth them such members? I answer, Their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible or audible, that is, their externall Engagement by Covenant to Christ: This (performed by the parent for them) is it on their part; supposing Christs Title to them, and the offer of himself in Covenant. If you ask me further, Why are meer externall Covenanters called by the name of the Church or Church-members? <hi>I</hi> answer, Because they do that which makes them appear to us to be Really members of the Church mystical. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> these words you have my sense as plainly as <hi>I</hi> can expresse it. (And <hi>I</hi> beleeve this is Mr. <hi>Marshals</hi> meaning in that one questioned Word in his
<pb n="385" facs="tcp:166114:9"/> late excellent, honest, solid Sermon for Unitie, where he denyeth all except the truly gracious to be Members of the Church, but acknowledgeth others such as we must use as Members) 2 The word [Appear] too is aequivocall. I speak not of any [seeming] in General; but of a [seeming] by the way that God hath appointed for manifestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, as by external Engagement, by Covenant, or by profession of Christianity. 3 Where he addeth [though not discerned by sense;] If he distinguish not between [discerned] and [discernable,] he speaks his own fictions, and not my sense. I know no way to the judgment, for such an object as a Church-member, but by the senses. But I do indeed affirm, that he is a visible Church-member, that perhaps is not seen or heard: For I never thought that <hi>omne visibile est visum:</hi> nor that a man ceaseth to be a visible member every time he is alone, out of the sight or hearing of others. Yet I think not that God hath any visible member in the World, but he hath been <hi>actualiter visus</hi> to be such, at one time or other, by some person other. For he that is the means of Converting him, or he that baptizeth him, or his parents that educate him, or some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body must needs discern these signs which God hath appointed to discover it. By <hi>[visible]</hi> therefore I mean not either, [a thing discerned by the intellect without the sense] as Mr. <hi>T.</hi> seems to suppose: nor yet [a thing meerly as visible to the eye, or discernable by other senses, without considering it as intelligible or discernable by the Intellect:] for then the Church were visible to Birds and Beasts. But by [visible] I mean, [that which is discernable by the Understanding <hi>mediante sensu,]</hi> there being in it a double Trope; 1 By a <hi>Synecdoche speciei</hi> [visible] is put for [sensible;] the most noble sense, for the rest; and its object for theirs. 2 And then sensible is put for intelligible <hi>mediante sensu.</hi> 4 He calls his ambiguous explication of an Adjective [a Definition] and saith, [by this the opposite terms Visible and Invisible, may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> If by [confusion] he means [a consistencie] <hi>in concreto</hi> in attribution to the same subject, I say, taking them as I have fully explained my meaning, <hi>&amp; eodem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectu,</hi> they are not consistent. Invisible and Visible are attributions from distinct reasons. The Church is invisible or mysticall in its Internall form, and sincere co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting with Christ: and it is visible in the matter and in the external Covenant and profession. But in these various respects I doubt not but the same Church and the same member, is both visible and mysticall. But if by [confusion] he mean, that visible and invisible, discernable and undiscernable (as explained) are terms of the same signification, or coincident; I shall more regard his affirmation when it is well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. 5. Were it not that I affect brevitie, I could by a multitude of Testimonies disprove his affirmation, that [I use the term Visible contrary to the common use of Writers,] if he mean Protestant Divines on this subject. 6 He saith, [he doubts not to shew that it is not true, that [he that is not of the visible Church, doth not seem (as I take the word seem) to be of the Invisible.] You may see by this what you must next expect from Mr. <hi>T. viz</hi> to prove, that [He that <hi>doth not seem</hi> to be of the invisible Church, <hi>doth seem</hi> to be of the invisible Church:] that he doth, and he doth not. Or that [he seemeth, (that is, is to be esteemed in probability upon Gods warrant and direction) to be of the Invisible Church, who neither by Covenant, profession nor any sign of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation doth make his membership seeming or discernable.] If I can understand him, that is it that he doubts not to prove. If he doth undertake to prove Heathens or any that are no Christians, to be seemingly in my sense (that is, so to be judged by a sign of Gods appointment) members of the Church mystical, and so to be members of Christs body, and to be saved; he will do a strange work; and I think will <hi>eodem co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natu,</hi> prove them members of the visible Church.</p>
               <pb n="386" facs="tcp:166114:10"/>
               <p> One word more. He is so offended at the next passage, that he saith [he knows not what to conceive of it, but that either by Gods judicial act of leaving me to my self, or out of addictedness to calumniate &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> And what are these words? Read them <hi>pag.</hi> 185. [But Mr. <hi>T.</hi> will say, I believe that it is better that Infants were no Christians, then that they were.] Where 1 I say not that he did say so. 2 Nor that he will (yet he vainly asks, [who can say but God, that he will say so for time to come, seeing he may repent] I wish he may repent. I only said that [I believed this would be his answer] Now whether I had reason to think so, let the Reader judge. Mr. <hi>T.</hi> denyeth Infants to be Disciples, and visible Church-members. I argued with him that if their Church-membership be repealed, it is in mercie or judgment; he said, In mercy. I replyed, If in mercy, then either to parents or children; and of them, to the elect or non elect: He answereth, Both to parents and children, to the elect and non-elect. I further proved that Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers visible, and Disciples are all one, and disciples and Christians all one, in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Scriptures. Have I not reason then to think that he that said Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, is revoked in mercie, and that it was better for them to be no Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, would say also that, It is better for them to be no Christians? But I am glad M. <hi>T.</hi> calls this [an Impious Speech] which I desire him to remember and to think so still. And then whereas he talks of such membership as the Iews had, I hope in his next he will tell the world some Reason of his opinion, if he think the Iews membership was worse then none: and he will tell us also, Whether it be in mercy or judgment, for the good or hurt of Infants, that Christ now denyeth them to be visible Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or such as he discovereth to us to be of his visible Church.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Ts.</hi> confident words about Infant-holiness in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14. shew me that it will not be unmeet to add a few words of the fuller explication of my meaning, lest in his next book he run on in the dark on mistaking suppositions. I described the holiness mentioned in that text thus, <hi>pag.</hi> 80. [A state of separation to God, as a peculiar-peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the world, as the Church is separated; wherein the Covenant or Promise of God being the chief cause, it is oft called [foederall holiness.] Now it seems to me that Mr. <hi>T.</hi> thinks that by this holiness, I mean meer visible Church-membership; and therefore concludes that visible membership cannot be conveyed to the child by an hypocrite parent, because I say that holiness cannot be so conveyed, and because I yeild that such are unholy, I must let him therefore understand. 1 That I take holiness there for much more then visible membership: Gods Promise or Covenant, as I said, is the ground of this holiness: but mans Covenanting or Profession is the Ground of the visibility of his membership. This holiness is Relative, and consisteth in being truly Relative to God, as a peculiar people; and truly so accepted by him; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving right to his promised favours in that Covenant, and the benefits that arise from the mutual Relation. But a man may (being a gross dissembler that creeps into the Church to spie out her liberties and to persecute) be a visible member. I confess I have not fully expressed how far this relation and Covenant doth interest them in Christ and his benefits: whether it only give them generall Grounds of Confidence in those words, [I will be thy God and thou my People] or [He will have mercie on thousands, &amp;c.] or, whether it be full Relative holiness, which hath the conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant Right to pardon and salvation, (which [I will be thy God] seemeth also to contain) I thought it not meet to be too peremptory or express in a Case so much disputed among divines: But I must confess I rather incline to think that it is (not Reall holiness which is the new Nature, but) that Relative Holiness which is proper to those in a Reconciled state; and that all true Believers Infants so dying are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="387" facs="tcp:166114:10"/> saved, being relatively in the same state with their parents: and that this Infant-relative holiness being on the conditionality of anothers faith, may be lost; (without any advantage to the Arminians in the doctrine of Perseverance of actual or habitual Believers.) I desire <hi>Davenants</hi> Epistle in Mr. <hi>Bedfords</hi> book may be weighed; and also Mr. <hi>Bedfords</hi> and Dr. <hi>Wards</hi> Tractate: though yet I continue my dissent in the points which I have opposed in them. I confess I am not able to answer the Arguments that are in my own mind, for a certainty of true-believers-infants remission and sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, if they dye before their Infant title ceaseth. But however it is apparent that holiness here is somewhat of far greater moment then visible membership. 2 I must next add, that as the word [Church] is taken aequivocally, sometime most properly and in its primary sense, for the true body of Christ (as invisible or visible;) and sometime in its remote, borrowed, less-proper sense, for the visible part, that is but vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible and not sincere; (as a picture is called a man, or as a woman is called your wife before the marriage, when it is next to concluding;) so the word [Holy] also hath the like double signification: 1 Primary, as it signifieth the Relation of one sincerely dedicated to God and owned by him. 2 Borrowed, or translated thence: as it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven (frequently by the Apostles) to those that seem to be holy in the first sense, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they so seem. 3 I add, that therefore the children of true Believers have that true relative holiness, which this text primarily intends: and therefore the children of seeming Believers, are seemingly holy in the first sense of the word, and truly holy in the latter, borrowed, less-proper sense; even as their parents are seemingly holy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and really in this sense. 4 I add that the ground of our baptizing is the express command of Christ, to [Disciple all Nations, Baptizing them,] and so to baptize all that are Disciples. 5 He hath not bid us baptize only sincere Disciples, nor told us that we must know them to be sincere before we baptize them. 6 He hath taught us by his Apostles constant example, to baptize those as Disciples that by a sober Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Christ, seem to be so. 7 He hath authorized them thus to Covenant for (and so Disciple) their infants with themselves. 8 I doe not therefore conclude the Baptizing of Infants directly from their holiness, as if that made the Duty: but from Christs precept directly; and from their holiness as that which infallibly assures me, that they are the due subjects of that Baptism which Christ commandeth; their holiness being either inseparably concomitant with Disciple-ship or eminently containing it; none but Disciples beng so holy. 9 And so (though Christ do Covenant with none but true Disciples; that is, to none other doth this Covenant actually convey right to its benefits; yet) as seeming Believers or Disciples are to be baptized, (being truly Disciples only in the borrowed sense) so I say of the seemingly holy, being indeed holy in the remote borrowed sense by reason of their seeming to be so in the first sense. And therefore though true Discipleship and holiness be the qualification which God looks at in conveying further Right by Baptism, or fealing it to them effectually; Yet it is the visibility of Discipleship and holiness (in the strict sense) which is the qualification which men must look after, (in their external Covenants and profession) and on which we must baptize them. And so I conclude, that though the infants of Hypocrites are not Disciples or holy in the strict sense, yet it is our duty to baptize them as being visibly such, as it was the Apostles duty to baptize the 3000. and <hi>Simon Magus;</hi> And Mr. <hi>T.</hi> cannot say that hypocrites convey not a visible membership to their Infanrs because they convey not the true holiness or Discipleship. And I desire Mr. <hi>T.</hi> when he answers me, to take my meaning as here opened to him.</p>
               <p>If any one else ask me, What we shall say of those that have a common faith which is yet undissembled though not saving; I answer, All faith not saving is defective either
<pb n="388" facs="tcp:166114:11"/> as to the objective Extension, or as to the active and habitual Intension. 1 Some do seriously believe in Christ, and consent to take him as a Saviour to pardon their sins by his blood and intercession, and to save them from hell at last, and to command them so far as will stand with their fleshly interest. These men may be serious in the Acts of Assenting and Consenting; but it is not Christ as Christ that they receive; not Christ as a full Saviour and Soveraign, absolutely and unreservedly to be obeyed, and therefore their faith hath not the object of a Christian faith: These men do not dissemble in saying they believe in Christ; but they dissemble in saying they believe in or receive Christ fully and sincerely as he is offered them: and they dissemble or speak falsly in saying they are true Christians. For indeed these men are but aequivocally and in a borrowed sense called Christians. Who will call a Turk a Christian, though he believe in Christ as a true and excellent Prophet of God, and though the Alcoran re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile the Jews for rejecting him? who will say that he becomes a subject, who is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to receive the King as his equal? 2 And as for those that doe profess to receive Christ intirely and in soveraigntie, and yet doe indeed preferre some fleshly interest before him, they are hypocritical as to the act it self; So that, though some dissemble grossely and knowingly, and others closely, not discerning it themselves: Yet all of them seem to be what they are not; and so all wicked men are properly Infidels (though not all in one degree,) some open Infidels, and some hypocritical ones; And so in strict sense none is a Christian but the true Christian; and others are only seeming Christians; yet called Christians usually in the foresaid borrowed sense. Indeed there are some that God is drawing towards Christ, who doe not dissemble: for they profess not yet to be his, (or if they doe, but counterfeit:) but these are not Christians indeed till they come quite over to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>§. 12.</head>
               <p>The summe of this Section, if I understand it, is, as if he said [I am resolved to goe that way which most successefully may promote the suppression of Infant-baptism; If Ministers will not hinder or cross me in that, but let me quietly carry it on, as Gods work, my heart is to have communion with them (and it shall not be said unlawfull) but because they resist me, I will separate from them, and prove that none but the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized should be admitted to communion:] supposing that they are unbaptized per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons. I doe not intend to trouble this with an answer. Only I would ask M. <hi>T.</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would not have taken it hainously if one had told him, after the writing of his three fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st books against baptism▪ that he would come to this now that he is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the same grounds as he will exclude us from Communion, he must not deny us to be Christians visible? and to have any thing to do with any Church Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? whether he must not affirm that we are no true Ministers? and that our Churches are no true Churches? and that Christ hath had no true Churches or Ministers on earth, but those very few that were baptized at age? and that all the Christians that have been converted, confirmed and saved by hearing Ministers that were baptized only in Infancie, did sin against God in hearing them, and ought to have refused it? Yea must he not on these grounds (if we are not Christians) deny to love us as Christians? or to doe any work of charity to any such as Christians? These Consequences practised are such a life as I would not wish Mr. <hi>T.</hi> to live. And for ought I see, they are as necessary consequents of his premisses as his own is: For if it be a good argument [It is manifest in Scripture that persons were baptized before they brake bread together &amp;c. therefore I see a necessity of desisting from uniting in Communion those that differ in Judgment about Infant Baptism;] then I would know
<pb n="389" facs="tcp:166114:11"/> whether he can name any in Scripture, that were true Christians, true Ministers of the Gospel, true Churches without baptism; or that were to be heard, loved, conversed with, and respected as such, without baptism? If he can name such, I doubt not but it will be proved that the same men brake bread together without baptism. If he can name none such, these consequences will follow as much as the other. Or if Mr. <hi>T.</hi> lay not the stress of his argument on this Scripture <hi>medium,</hi> but on our opposition to him (for in such a conjunction of heterogeneous Mediums, I am not sure that I know his mind,) yet I am sure this is the usual way of others of that party. So Mr. <hi>Cox</hi> one of their Pastors in <hi>London</hi> disputed with me in writing [we may not be heard preach, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we are unbaptized.] And I think Mr. <hi>T.</hi> heard Mr. <hi>Brown</hi> sately at <hi>Worcester</hi> goe the same way; maintaining his communion with those that accused the Scriptures of falshood; and that <hi>Paul</hi> might pray among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> though some were drunk at the Lords Supper, and some eat things offered to Idols and Devils, and some denyed the Resurrection &amp;c. but that now they may not pray in our mixt Assemblies, because we are unbaptized. Is it not evident that Rebaptizing is become the great Idol which men set up in stead of Christ, or a sound faith, or a holy life? Prove to them that there are in their own Assemblies, men that reproach or denie Scriptures, denie the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of the soul, denie Christs Ordinances, (and consequently have not Christ with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them,) yet they may have communion with them because they are in the order of the Gospel (as they call it) that is Rebaptized and separated: But with us they may not communicate though never so godly, because we are unbaptized! Was ever Infants-baptism Idolized thus? or abused to this height, by any that pretend to be knowing reformed Divines?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>§. 13.</head>
               <p>To all the angry passages here, I say but this: 1 I desire not to think Mr. <hi>T.</hi> means worse then he doth. If I mistook his meaning, I am sorry that I spoke so offensively, and repent the mistake, and the sharp words that it occasioned. 2 But let the Reader peruse his words, and see whether he gave me not cause to interpret them as I did. When in the midst of a Dispute about the Monsters in <hi>New-England,</hi> he saith, [Nay give me leave to tell you, we may rather think we ought to determine, that God may order accidents so, as to become stumbling blocks that people should not receive the truth rather then &amp;c.] who would think that he spoke not here of these monsters? or that these words doe not charge God with a purposed leading men into error by wonders?</p>
               <p>In my Epistle I shewed my hearers the danger of a perverted judgment, that it will make the hainousest sin seem a vertue, and men think they do God service in killing his Saints, &amp;c. which Christ hath said himself before me: What doth Mr. <hi>T.</hi> but say, In all likelihood I speak of thanksgivings for victories against the Scots; and so dilate on those providences? To which I only say, 1 I desire Mr. <hi>T.</hi> to deal with my words, and not to pretend to know my thoughts. If I had said this much of him, I doubt he would have said, I stirred up the State against him, with a persecuting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent (at least) if I had said what he hath privatelyer said of me, which I can prove. Some have observed that the Rebaptizers waters usually turn to blood, and their hands incline much to a crimson dye: and that they are much bent to the baptizing of all men; their Proselytes <hi>baptismate fluminis;</hi> and the rest <hi>baptismate sanguinis.</hi> I think not that all are of this mind. 2 I must tell Mr. <hi>T.</hi> that I despise not the strange providences of this age, but observe them, and acknowledge and admire God in them,
<pb n="390" facs="tcp:166114:12"/> and discern him testifying against the sins of the destroyed. But I suppose the full in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of them is not so obvious as in the case we were upon: Nor do I find in Scripture that it is Gods usual course to choose a holy, humble, meek people to be the executioners of his severest judgments on his Church. When we have sinned our selves into a necessity of such calamities, God usually chooseth executioners whose na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures fit and dispose them to the work. Were I to kill a Hare, I would not send a Lamb to do it; or to kill a Partridge, I would not send a Dove. And I here pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly and fearlesly tell the world, that <hi>[I take it for one of the remarkable and most hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py providences of this age, that when he had such strange iudgments to execute as we have seen, he hath chosen out such instruments to be his executioners, and would not suffer those to have a hand in them, who thereby might have brought a scandal on the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and hath so gratiously ordered it, that if any Turk, Jew, or Papist shall dare to say hereafter, [Your Reformed Orthodox Christians did these things] their notorious impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonments and seclusions will vindicate them for ever.</hi> When God hath in mercie again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved on a healing work, he will then make use of prudent, compassionate, healing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments. And for the Common-wealth, Mr. <hi>T.</hi> may sit in his chair and talk for them, with less trouble, danger, charge, or pain, then I have acted for them, and yet perhaps with more thanks.</p>
               <p>And seeing there is so much offence taken about the matrer of wonderful provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, which I mentioned, I add this much more; I cannot but with joy and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence look on the hand of God, against the erroneous ways of these times. Was it not the all-disposing Lover of Truth who chose out these two leading women in <hi>New-England,</hi> the one to bring forth such a multitude of births at once, and the other a birth with such various parts, some of birds, some of beasts, some of fishes, and some of man; hereby to shew his testimonie against their various abominations? Though Mrs. <hi>Hutchinson</hi> said, [God did it to harden us,] I think he did it to confirm his truth. The remembrance whereof makes me hope that the same God will yet appear in Old <hi>England,</hi> against the same Cause, and (some say) the same Agents. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he doth appear, and hath already done such wonders as astonish me to observe them; giving up the minds of some, and the bodies also of others to such a power of the Devils, that some have such strange shakings and trances; and such a multitude in so many parts of the Land, turn Ranters, Blasphemers, commonly unclean that seemed religious: yea, some turn down-right Infidels; so that not only the <hi>Racovian Catechism,</hi> but the most hellish book that ever I heard of (called <hi>The three Grand Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postors,</hi> thought to be written by <hi>Bernardinus Ochinus)</hi> labouring to prove Christ a Deceiver, is translated, and printed in <hi>London.</hi> And lest men should doubt of the truth of these Delusions, God permitteth a woman to run naked into the Assembly, the men to goe about rhe streets, saying they are Christ, and their wickedness to spread far and near; so that it is sometimes the matter of the Weekly Pamphlets to proclaim it, besides others that publish it for the warning of the godly; as Justice <hi>Stoaks</hi> in his <hi>Wiltshire</hi> Rant, and other like. Doubtless God shews himself against them apparently, and hath done very much hereby against them already. And I cannot hear of one among a multitude that comes to this fearful pass by another way▪ then first turning to Anabap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>istry and Separation, and then usually to villifie the Ministry, and so to Antinomianism, and then who knows whether? I dare not shut mine eyes against such providences, in an age when so many call us to the study of providence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="391" facs="tcp:166114:12"/>
               <head>§. 14.</head>
               <p>I need to say but this; It is particular men, and not any supposed societie which consisteth not of particulars, that are known by their fruits, though not every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular man. That one mans doctrine may be shamed by the life of his companions, though not by his own; And there are signs probable as well as certain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>§. 15.</head>
               <p>The answer to the 13. §. shall serve for this also; only adding this: That I should more readily ask Mr. <hi>T.</hi> forgiveness of my sharp language against Anabaptists, if the most of them in <hi>England</hi> were as he and his partie here: But when I look about me on <hi>England, Scotland, Holland, &amp;c.</hi> and consider what they have done, and what it is certain they are attempting, and like to doe, (were it but against the Ministry of Christs Gospel) I am afraid of being guilty that I have not dealt yet plainly enough; having just cause to fear that yet <hi>England</hi> hath not tasted the worst of them, how fairly soever Mr. <hi>T.</hi> may smooth the business. I would I had known the accidents of this year, which he saith <hi>(pag.</hi> 62.) may wipe away the reproach of them, as to the disobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (thats an easie word) of Governours that doe not please them! sure he must be a potent Rhetorician that makes this age believe them so obedient, whatsoever the next may doe. Else Mr. <hi>T.</hi> could not have said as now he doth, <hi>pag.</hi> 60. [Those that sit at the Sterm, I cannot yet learn, have such hard thoughts of them as Mr. <hi>B.]</hi> Against which assertion I confess my self unfit to dispute. Unless I were neerer the Stern, or knew them better, or had spoke with any that knows who sits there. But if he had said, [Those that did sit at the Stern] I would have considered of the reasons that moved them to think better of them, and have enquired whether by this time their judgments be not changed, or like to be ere long? and whether they will with Mr. <hi>T.</hi> subscribe to their innocencie, obedience, fidelitie, and give them his acquittance?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>§. 16.</head>
               <p>His confidence <hi>pag.</hi> 66. is marvellous. I doubt not but he knows that I take the words, [since the solemn institution of baptism, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.] inclusively. And so I answer, that this solemn Institution is our Warrant, requiring us both to Disciple Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and baptize Disciples. And we have other Scriptures which plainly prove In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants to be Disciples. To that he calls a calumnie, <hi>pag.</hi> 67. I say, He chose those which in my judgment were the weakest Arguments. That threatning which he cals a tale-tellers fiction, <hi>pag.</hi> 68. is in his own letters to me: though since then I could name him men of note far and near, to whom he hath used against me much more of that language.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>§. 17.</head>
               <p>I know not one word of Answer that this §. needs for him that will peruse any words.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>§. 18.</head>
               <p>Nor shall I say any thing to this, but trouble the Reader with our Letters in the end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>§. 19.</head>
               <p>To the first error, I am glad you shew your meaning to be better then your words,
<pb n="392" facs="tcp:166114:13"/> whether by explication or recantation. Where he saith, [I presume they that sit at the Stern, do find the so-called Anabaptists as faithfull to the publick Cause as their Opposites,] I will not deny it, till I am so well skilled in Politicks, as to understand [what the publick cause] means; and whether [the stern] signifies strength or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and how far violence and faithfulness may consist.</p>
               <p>To the second, about Lay-mens baptism he saith nothing that I know that needs any answer.</p>
               <p>To the third about Lay-mens administring the Lords Supper, he contents himself with strange Answers. 1 He pleads that Ruling Elders, and Deacons have Church Administrations. But he might know 1 That the question is (in my meaning) of this Administration. 2 That Elders and Deacons are Christs Officers, and he doth ill to call them [Lay.] Our question is of members not in office. 2 He asks <hi>pag.</hi> 81. [how is it proved that Ministers only should represent Christs person in breaking bread, delivering it to all, bidding, Take, Eat, &amp;c? Doth the Embassage of Christ, dispensing of his mysteries, beseeching in his stead, consist in breaking bread, deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, bidding Take, Eat?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 Christ did not perform this action as a common person, but as Head; and therefore they only that are commissioned to speak in his name and stead, must do it. Let any other shew their Commission. 2 The Embassage to the Believers doth consist partly in this, Take, Eat, &amp;c. He argues to the contrary thus, [If it doe, then a non-preaching Minister who doth these things, may yet be an Embassador of Christ.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> If by [Preaching] you mean publishing and teaching to men the doctrine of Christ, I know no such thing as a non preaching Minister. 2 What if it be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that he that is not sent on the Embassage of publick proclaiming Christ to the world, be yet sent to bid the Believers of a particular Church Take, and Eat? He adds [then breaking bread is a converting ordinance, as Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> held.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> If you mean, that it <hi>may</hi> convert; who ever denyed it? yea or it may be usuall to convert unsound Christians to sincerity. But if you mean, that this is the direct end to which it is instituted, to convert men from Infidelity, yea or from Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie,] you may easily say, but when will you prove that this followeth? Doth Christ send Ministers to do nothing but convert? Have they no message peculiar to Believers? Doth <hi>Chamier</hi> by <hi>[ipso signo]</hi> mean the whole Sacrament?</p>
               <p>But <hi>pag.</hi> 82. he saith [M. <hi>B.</hi> saith so, that the Sacrament revealeth the mystery of God to the eye, but not one text of Scripture saith so, nor is it true: The mystery contains not only the thing done by Christ; but the end, use, reason of it: but this is perceivable only by the understanding, and the Sacrament abstractively from that word declares it not; no not so much as a picture: and therefore the Sacramental Actions of themselves, are not the revelations of the mysteries of Christ, nor ever so called in the Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 If the receiving actions do declare the mysteries of the Gospel, then the administring actions do: But the receiving actions do, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 26. <hi>As oft as ye eat this bread and drink this cup, ye do shew the Lords death till he come.</hi> Are not eating and drinking, actions? and is is not Christs death and comming part of the Gospel myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? and was it not Christs death with its end, (the expiation of sin,) and his coming with the end, (the glorifying and fully delivering the Saints) that is here meant? but only the meer Death and Comming, without the reason, ends, or use? And is not this text Scripture? 2 Do you think that the Sacrament consisteth only in action, distinct from words? Are words no actions? or no part of the sacramentall action? Is not saying, [Take, Eat, this is &amp;c.] as reall a part as breaking the bread? 3 Doe
<pb n="393" facs="tcp:166114:13"/> not you therefore describe a Sacrament which Christ never instituted, if you say, it consisteth of actions without words? 4 We distinguish between the words which are part of this ordinance, [Take, Eat, this is my body which is &amp;c.] and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> words of a Sermon, or other doctrine not essentiall to the Sacrament. The Sacrame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> might sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie without one, though not without the other. 5 Did Mr. <hi>T.</hi> think that I make the eye an Intellect to see Reasons, Ends and Uses? Or knew he not that I mean, [It sheweth by the eye to the Intellect?] 6 Doth he indeed think, that the Word reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth truths immediately to the Intellect? Let him speak to the deaf and try? 7 Can he tell me in what kind of causality the Word works, which the Sacrament doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so work in? Doth the Voice by any natural power of its own, acquaint the understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with truths? I think it works but <hi>per modum signi,</hi> as a sign of the speakers mind: And that it is not a naturall sign (for then children would speak without teaching,) but an instituted: when men by agreement do impose such a sense on such a word, and by custome use it to signifie such a notion, then it is fit to reveal that notion by the ear to the Intellect: And when they change the custome and use it to another sense, then it loseth its aptitude to the former: So that words are (under God) in mens own power to signifie what they please. (And I think if all the learned men in the world that use one language (as the Latine) would in a Councel by their Delegates, fix a common sense of most useful and controverted words, it would be a most excellent work, and the best Dictionary that ever was made.) And may not God impose a sense upon an action of the Hand, as well as on a Voice? Nay, hath he not done it? Doth Mr. <hi>T.</hi> think that Dipping, and Washing have no imposed signification? or that they signifie only to the eye, and not the Intellect? Is it not usual for the dumb to discover their mind by signs? In which way some will readily and ordinarily discourse. Nay, I would know, if you will needs look to the Nature of the thing, without Institution or Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, Whether the Sacramentall actions be not more significant then the words? Let Mr. <hi>T.</hi> speak of Christ crucified to an Indian that never heard word of his language, and I think he will make him understand more by other signs then by words.</p>
               <p>Also I would know of him what he thinks of Scripture, which is no Voice, but a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible sign; may it not teach the mysteries of Christ? And hath not he that made those words the signifyers of his mysteries, made the Sacramental Elements &amp; actions so too? saying, <hi>[This is my body which is broken for you, do this in remembrance of me.]</hi> Sure Mr. <hi>T.</hi> interprets <hi>[This is my body]</hi> as the Reformed Divines doe, by <hi>[This signifieth my body;]</hi> I hope he doth. And what if I say, that Words are the Primary sign (as the written in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument in Law cases) and the Sacramental actions the secondary, (as the seal an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed,) it would not follow that Sacraments declare not the mysterie; Though indeed as to the matter of signification they both work in one kind of causality; though God have instituted one in a kind of subserviencie to the other.</p>
               <p>And where Mr. <hi>T.</hi> addes, that [he thinks to be Stewards of the mysteries, is all one as to preach the Gospel,] I would have him better consider two things. 1 That part of the Gospel is proper to Believers. 2 That the very substance of the Gospel is more closely and exactly comprised in the Sacraments then any where else that I know. The expiatory sacrifice is there represented, with the sacrificing actions, and then follows the substance of the Covenant it self, [Take, Eat, this is my, &amp;c.] The Gospel is the Revelation and offer of Christ and his benefits; which is all here done. If that be Gospel <hi>[Let him that is thirsty come and drink &amp;c.]</hi> then this is. Doubtless it is not the meer bread that Christ bids us Take, but Himself, with pardon of sin, and right to sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. And <hi>Paul</hi> talks of the <hi>Galathians,</hi> as [before whose <hi>eyes</hi> Jesus Christ hath been evidently set forth crucified among them] not only to their ears, but their eyes. Though
<pb n="394" facs="tcp:166114:14"/> I deny not (but as <hi>Grotius)</hi> words may be here chiefly meant, yet I see not but Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and miracles must be included. At least Mr. <hi>T.</hi> will not deny but in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, 26. [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] is a declarative action. I conclude therefore that if it be the act of an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fficer to represent Christ ordinarily in his solemn stated worship, Giving himself and benefits to his Church, then this in hand is such: If it be not, there is no act of office at all, and so no officer.</p>
               <p>His answer to my second Argument is as strange as the former. I say, [If there be no command or example in Scripture of any but Ministers administring the Lords Supper, then no others may do it; but &amp;c.] 1 He tels me of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28. <hi>Let a man Examine himself, and so eat,]</hi> Is this a proof? or should Mr. <hi>T.</hi> so importunately expect that other men should be satisfied with that that satisfieth him? The Question is whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther private men may administer it; and he proves they may eat. Eating presupposeth Administring, and Taking presupposeth Christs Giving by his Representers. When God saith <hi>[Hear and your soul shall live,]</hi> It doth not allow them to preach, nor sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose a hearing without preaching. And whereas Mr. <hi>T.</hi> saith <hi>pag.</hi> 70. his chief ground is 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 20, 21. that in eating every one took his own supper before other, and this could not have happened if they had been wont to receive it from a Minister that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stributed to all. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I Reply, 1 All (that I know of) are agreed that the 27. <hi>v.</hi> speaks of their eating at their Love-feasts before the Sacrament, where the old communitie begun to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, and every one eat and drink of his own, and so the poor did hunger. Yet the Sacrament was abused by this, they having such a connexion, and there being such a division at the entrance on it. And it was in regard to this feast that the Apostle bids them tarry for one another: that if they would feast publickly, they should doe it in communitie; if not, do it at home. 2 Why might not those that came not in together, receive that which was blest and delivered to the Church? We say not that it was put into particular mens hands. 3 It is so far from being probable (as he conceits) that there were no elders, that its most probable the number of them was great; and that these Elders were the chief in the divisions; and then each partie might easily receive it. (As appears in <hi>Clem. Roman. Epist.</hi> to them, where he is fain to advise the Elders to administer by turns, because they could not agree.) There were many Prophets <hi>ch.</hi> 14. and they were Church guides: And the Apostles that ordained Elders in every Church, left not this without Christs order and ordinances: Nor do any of the Texts that he cites give any probability of it.</p>
               <p>(But I marvell how Mr. <hi>T.</hi> should <hi>pag.</hi> 91. [think that the Presbyterians and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents agree with Papists about the sufficiencie of Baptism by Priests or Weomen, because they doe not question their baptism nor seek any other] when yet he pleads that other may administer both Sacraments, besides Ministers: Why then should it be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nullity because done by a Priest or Woman, if his way be right?) Next he citeth 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16, 17. But he knows that when the whole Church is mentioned, it is usuall to say, They do that which the nobler part doth: By [We bless] is meant the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers act, and by [We are partakers] the Peoples and Officers reception. When we say [This Commonwealth doth command and maintain their Armie] the meaning is, the Ruling part commands it, but the whole maintain it. Mr. <hi>T.</hi> addes [But for command or example that an ordained Presbyter only should Administer the Lords Supper, let them that say there is, shew it.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. The question is of Ministers as opposed to private men; and therefore you should not thrust in the terms [ordained Presbyters.] It is a doubt whether Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation be of such necessity to the Being of a Minister, that in case of necessity he
<pb n="395" facs="tcp:166114:14"/> may not be without it. 2 The same man is not the same when he looks another way. Doubtless the Will hath a great power over the Understanding it self. <hi>I</hi> prove that Ministers did administer this Sacrament; and Mr. <hi>T.</hi> denyeth it not. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> put him to prove that any other ever did it; and he cannot. And yet he would have me moreover prove that only Ministers did it; that is, Prove the nega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive in the matter of fact; <hi>viz.</hi> that others did not: or prove the positive exclusion in matter of warrant; that is, not only that others can shew no commission, but that they are forbidden. But Sir, why wil you not then admit the like reasoning in point of Infant Baptism? Do you shew com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or example that the aged only should be baptized? And doe not then press us still to shew command or example that Infants should be baptized. But for my part, I shall yeild to prove my assertion in both, and have done.</p>
               <p>I yet adde this: If Circumcision were a sign and seal of the righteousness of faith, then it so far declared the mystery of Faith; and if it may declare it, why may not Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Sacraments much more?</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Ts.</hi> next words please me more then all the angry words that ever I had from him (to my self) in Press or Pulpit displease me. I will write them in full Characters, and intreat all those in Parliament, Army, City, or Country, that may be concerned in the matter, to lay them to heart, and prevent this guilt and curse: and those that value Mr. <hi>Ts.</hi> judgment, to regard it here. <hi>[Pastors and Teachers</hi> or <hi>Presbyters to teach and govern the Church of God, I am assured are a Divine Institution, and a very mercifull gift of Christ,</hi> Eph. 4. 11. 12, 13. 1 Cor. 12. 28. Act. 14. 23. 1 Tim. 3. 1. Tit. 2. 5. <hi>to whom people should yeild obedience,</hi> Heb. 13. 17. <hi>and yeild maintenance liberally,</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 14. Gal. 6. 6. 1 Tim. 5. 17. 18. <hi>If any goe about to extirpate them, let him be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed as an enemy to Christ and his Church.]</hi> I adde, [Eccept they repent; however let their design be blasted and accursed:] Oh let the Churches Guardian say <hi>Amen.</hi> It was Gods providence that even when the Pharisees ask their Missionaries <hi>[Do any of the Rulers or Pharisees believe in him?]</hi> there should be a <hi>Nicodemus</hi> at their elbow to contradict them, by taking his part. And if it be now asked, [Doe any called Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists speak for the Ministry, their Government and maintenance?] here is Mr. <hi>T.</hi> pronouncing them accursed as Christs enemies that goe about to extirpate them.</p>
               <p>But let me say to him, that I fear much lest the Design laid by him <hi>pag.</hi> 79. may doe more to this cursed work, then this curse will hinder it. <hi>viz.</hi> His pretending [a neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity that persons not ordained yet Preachers of the Gospel, do baptize] (Though the words are a most compleat aequivocation, as ever was uttered at <hi>Delphos:</hi> You may take it, [not ordained yet to be Preachers, or [not ordained, but yet Preachers,] but I rather take it in the last sense.) If once those that are no Ministers, must of necessity be preachers and baptizers, and may administer Sacraments, and the Juridical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (as he calls it) denyed Ministers; and all the Ministers that are against Rebaptizing judged to cause this necessity; how short a step is it, if not to the direct extirpation of the office, yet at least of all those persons? and then where will Mr. <hi>T.</hi> find men enough, of tolerable parts to supply their places? some think Mr. <hi>Ts.</hi> design here, is now on the wheel for execution. Ministers medling with State matters I am against as well as Mr. <hi>T.</hi> so be it he will give me leave to meddle with Church mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Christs matters, and sin: and so he do not as I have known some, <hi>viz.</hi> when the Act for sequestring all that kept not the appointed dayes of Humiliation and Thanksgiving was out, and Ministers durst not keep them because they understood not State mysteries, and the cause of the Scottish wars, they were blazed to be med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers with State matters, when they were <hi>quoad legem,</hi> sequestred for not medling with State matters, and that before they understood them, and that in an extraordinary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to God.</p>
               <pb n="396" facs="tcp:166114:15"/>
               <p> I think the ministerial Government, is not properly called Juridicall. And I doe not much dissent from what is here said about the preaching of those that are not in Office; t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough I should have fullyer explained it.</p>
               <p>The 4. and 5. Errors which Mr. <hi>T.</hi> puts by, I had rather have dealt with him about, then any of the rest: But seeing he waves them now, I must follow him.</p>
               <p>To the 6. Error [that Magistrates are not under Christ as Mediator] I intreat the Reader to see how well he answereth what I have said: and whether he doth not repeat his words which I have already answered, without taking notice of their answer. 1 I shewed him where Magistrates have a commission from Christ. 2 When he saith [then no Infidel is a lawful Magistrate that denyes Christ] He knew I answered this; but thrusts his repetitions on less careful Readers. He may as well argue [then no magistrate is from the true God, who denyes the true God.] 3 He saith [then a Magistrate doing of right to an Infidel against a Believer, or to one Believer against another, as putting him to death, is an act for Christ as Mediator.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply</hi> I had hoped no sober Christian had denyed it; I fear this doctrine makes so little done for Christ: But if men once cease to acknowledg their tenure from, and dependance on Christ, and think it their duty to stand Newters, between him and Mahomet or Infidels, let them look to their standing, and wonder not if he be as little for them, yea if he manifest his authority by judging and consuming them: For if his wrath be kindled, yea, but a little—. 4 He addes; [then a fathers power over his child; but sure that is by Nature.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Did not I already answer this? Nature it self is now committed to Christ, for all things are in his hands. The pillars of the earth are born by him. He saith, He thinks I have not answered these. And I say thats a short Reply. 5. He addes [then if Christ had not been Mediator, there had been no lawfull Magistrate.] And why so? May they not be lawfull under God Creator under the first Covenant, though they be all under God Redeemer since the Law of Grace? 6 He addes [then <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum fundatur in Gratiâ.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Most cerrain: But in <hi>Gratiâ Redemptionis &amp; universali: non in Gratiâ speciali sanctificationis vel adoptionis:</hi> except you speak of the peculiar right of Saints above others. 7 He yet addes [May not Believers entitle themselves to all Power and all mens estates?]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Believers have no power but derived from Christ, as they are heirs: but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivatively, and not as Christ. And therefore how can they have that power or estate which Christ never gave them propriety in; yea, hath given to others, and forbid them to usurp? so much of that.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>§. 20.</head>
               <p>The Ancients took Infant-baptism, as you say, for an Apostolical Tradition, but not unwritten. The warrant they supposed written; but not the History <hi>de facto.</hi> You might have spared all the 86. <hi>pag.</hi> where you prove that Papists take it for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written Tradition. We know they are desirous of any pretence to set Tradition above Scripture. Yet you know <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and others commonly prove it by Scripture. The words of <hi>Becanus</hi> (not §. 24. as you say, but §. 12.) yeeld, the text rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted to prove Infant-baptism, and thats all that I desire. I had thought that <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miers</hi> answer to this might have satisfied you! If you have forgot it, peruse it again, <hi>Tom.</hi> 7. <hi>lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. §. 40. <hi>&amp;c. &amp; Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 9. §. 31. Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> hath made you know he is of another judgment. Mr. <hi>Bedford</hi> tells me he hath corrected his words
<pb n="397" facs="tcp:166114:15"/> in a later Edition. How could you alledge Dr. <hi>Field</hi> without considering how you wronged your self? Is nothing written in Scripture but expresly? Yea, is not that Scripture proof and plain proof, which shewes plainly from Scripture the Grounds, Reasons, and Causes of the Necessitie of the practice? Dr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> thought Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacie proveable from Scripture: and therefore if he thought that Infant-baptism must be proved the same way, he is sure against you. For Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> if you have read all his Books, I hope you will no more reckon him among Protestants, having so much of the Body of Popery in them. Mr. <hi>Youngs</hi> words (if they be his) are against you in the thing you cite them for. There are <hi>testimonia minùs aperta:</hi> and there are <hi>testimonia aperta pro fundamento &amp; praemissis, quae sunt minus aperta directè pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conclusione.</hi> My audaciousness in asserting plaine Scripture proof must be better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed then thus, if you will satisfie men of reason and conscience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>§. 21.</head>
               <p>I shall pass over all the words that require no answer. He saith <hi>pag.</hi> 93. [for the tenet of the Peoples governing by vote, I know no Reason why they should be called a Sect rather then their opposites,]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> But doe they not erre more then their opposites? Did not you even now prove from Scripture that Ministers must govern the Church, and the people obey them? Can that stand with the Peoples Governing? Is it so small a matter to arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the Ministerial Office? and consequently destroy it? You pronounced them even now accursed as enemies to Christ that goe about to extirpate the Ministry. The Lord keep you from drawing any of that curse on your self. But lay altogether and see what use you leave for a Ministry. [1 Others may baptize: yea, there is a necessity (because the Minister will not rebaptize, &amp;c.) that some not ordained, yet preachers, do it. 2 Others may administer the Sacrament of the Supper. 3 Others may preach publickly. 4 And if the people may and ought to govern, what is a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry to be upheld for? Or at least, how fair a way is here to their extirpation? He adds [The excommunication which the Scripture speaks of, so far as I discern, is no where made a part of Government, or of the Elders office any more then the peoples.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> The term Excommunication, is not in the Scripture; but that which is aequipollent is: when a man is obstinate in a hainous sin, after private admonition and publick, should not the Minister charge the people in Christs name to avoid fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar communion with them? and is this no more a part of the Elders office then the peoples? must not the Minister do it as an authoritative act of an Officer of Christ, which <hi>clave non errante</hi> the people are doubly bound to obey? not only <hi>ratione ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriae,</hi> (as they must from another) but also by virtue of the 5. Commandement, and that of Christ. [He that despiseth you despiseth me?] We allow the people <hi>judicium discretionis</hi> whether the Minister speak according to Scripture: and we allow them <hi>actualem executionem,</hi> by an obedient avoiding the communion of the partie: But have they also the authoritative judgment of discretion, guidance, Commanding non-communion <hi>ex officio</hi> in Christs name? or have Ministers none such? Do you think Ministers have any more power then others in preaching? If they have, then why not about this subject as well as others? to apply the command [with such no not to eat] to particular persons, and charge the people to obey? what is that govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which even now you gave to Ministers? If it lie not in authoritative guidance, and charging on men the duties prescribed by Christ, I know not what it is: And how falls it out that it extendeth not to the duty of avoiding communion with such persons, as well as to other duties? Also, should not Ministers declare to wicked
<pb n="398" facs="tcp:166114:16"/> men their miserie and Gods wrath by a particular application? And is not this part of it? May I not pronounce an obstinate sinner to be a child of the Devil as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Elimas?</hi> or to be in the gall of bitterness, and bond of iniquitie, and have no part or fellowship, &amp;c. as <hi>Peter</hi> did <hi>Simon?</hi> or one that is in an unjustified state? at least, one that with whom the Church should have no familiar Communion? And doth this belong no more to the Elders then the people? are the keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven given as much to private Christians as to Officers? or do not the keys reach to this? When <hi>Paul</hi> charged the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to cast out <hi>(executivè)</hi> that wicked person, did he no more then belonged to the people? But you say [In antiquity its appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent out of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that the people had a great hand in Elections, Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Absolutions.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1 As to Elections; the peoples consent is <hi>conditio sine qua non</hi> to the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion successfully of the ministerial office: and this <hi>Naturaliter,</hi> and not directly <hi>per institutionem.</hi> For who can rule a Peoples Wills against their wills? Consent is the success of perswasion: and therefore the peoples consent must be the like condition of the plenary title of an Elder over a particular Church. But whats this to authority of government? to consent to soveraigntie is not to be a Soveraign. 2 When the Church had no Christian Magistrates, how could any man be guide to a People but by their consent? or cast out, or take in successfully without it? 3 Did you ever read in <hi>Cyprian,</hi> or any man worth the reading in all Antiquity, that the people had any more in excommunicating and absolving, then to judge <hi>per judicium discretionis,</hi> and to consent to the Officers authoritative censure, and obediently to execute it by hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing communion, or avoiding it? 4 Doe you not find it frequently in <hi>Cyprian</hi> that there is an Excommunication and Absolution which are parts of government, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long more to the Officers then the People? Yea, and such rigid censures (keeping men so long before they would absolve them after a fall, though they begged it in great poenitence; and sharply taking up the very Confessors that presumed to intercede for their readmission) that were they now used, what Tyrants, and Popes and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christs should we be called? who would have thought that Mr. <hi>T.</hi> that hath said so much to the contrary, should say so much for Popular Church-government? He adds [Nor is a person a Separatist for that Tenet, but for dividing practises.] 1 I had thought he had been a Separatist in judgment, that doth not practise his judgment. 2 Is it not a dividing practice to practise popular Voting Government? Nay worse then actual Separation, as subverting the very essence of Christs Offices, if not Churches. I confess I doubt whether that can be a true particular political Church of Christ where the Government is in the peoples Vote. For every such Church essentially consisteth (as a Common-wealth doth) of a <hi>Pars Dirigens &amp; Nunciativè imperans, &amp; Pars di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recta &amp; imperata.</hi> And in Christs Church the former are his Officers.</p>
               <p>Yet let me add, that we give the people the same things (in their <hi>judicium discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis,</hi> and in execution) which sober congregational men desire. Only we are ready to prove, it is not Government strictly so called.</p>
               <p>As to the next passage about <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 16. Your answer is more and more strange. When I prove clearly a [false Teacher] and [one that teacheth falsly] to be the same; you will disprove it by saying that [a false Teacher] and [hearing false doctrine] are not the same. As if it would prove the objects to be divers, because the object and sense or manner of Reception be divers! or as if it had been Christs end to tell by what sense they might come to know false Teachers, <hi>viz</hi> by Hearing; and not by what sign! When the question was whether the coldness of the water, or whiteness of the wall were a sign by which you discern it to be cold, white? or the form so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominating
<pb n="399" facs="tcp:166114:16"/> it? You talk of [feeling] the coldness, and [seeing] the whiteness; as if that were any thing to the question, which was not <hi>de Receptione,</hi> but <hi>de objecto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But (though I dare not be suddenly confident, yet) me thinks, I now (with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness) see my mistake about this Text. And it did lie in the misunderstanding the word <hi>[Pseudo-propheta,</hi> false prophet] 1 I took [Prophet] to be same with [Teacher] and 2 I took [false] to be spoken of him <hi>ab opere,</hi> from his doctrine, and not a <hi>dese<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu formâ &amp; authoritate,</hi> with a pretence of the contrary. I inconsideratly judged as <hi>Paraeus in loc.</hi> that <hi>Propheta est Doctor Veritatis. Pseudo-propheta Doctor mendacii,</hi> and as <hi>Piscator,</hi> that these false Prophets were <hi>falfi Doctores qui Ecclesie proponunt dogmata exitialia.</hi> So also <hi>Calvin,</hi> &amp;c. But I now think 1 that the word [Prophet] is not taken for a Teacher as such; but in the strict and usual sense, for [one sent of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily to lead men out of Errour, or bring men to some speciall Reformation, as receiving his Doctrine, or his Commission, or both, by an immediate Inspiration or Revelation from Heaven.] 2 That they are called [false] as we call the Papists <hi>[Pseudo-catholicos]</hi> or others <hi>[Pseudo-christianos;]</hi> that is, they are counterfeit Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: they pretend falsly to be sent or inspired by God; and so to be Prophets, when they are no Prophets. As if a man come to a City in the Kings name, and say, He is a Herald, Embassadour, or special Messenger: and another say, Take heed of him; he is a counterfeit Messenger: the King sent him not. Now in this sense, it is plain that [his Doctrine] may be one of the fruits we may know him by, and it is not <hi>idem per idem,</hi> as I said, and as in the former sense it must be. And I the rather now incline to this Interpretation also, because I resolve that <hi>Austins</hi> rule must be followed, of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting Scripture in the most comprehensive sense, where there is no special reason for a restriction or limitation: And therefore I shall take the [fruits] in Generall, as applyable either to Doctrine or Life, without restraining it to either, as <hi>Deodate</hi> doth, and the New Annotations (and not as most interpreting it of doctrine alone; nor as some, of practice alone.) Yet I am stil perswaded that the Text intendeth practice as much if not much more then Doctrine; And for the Doctrine which I delivered hence, it is fully manifest in several other Scriptures. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> give us the description of the Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of those times, as men of enormous lives. And <hi>Paul</hi> prophesies that they shall hold the same course in the last times. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1. to the 10. It was they that having a form of godliness without the power do creep into houses, and lead captive silly women laden with sins, and led away with divers lusts, ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth, &amp;c. who, were the self-lovers, covetous, boasters, proud, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy, without natural affection, truce▪ breakers▪ false-accusers, incontinent, fierce, dispisers of the good, traitors, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleasures above God. These are the fruits they shall be known by. And it is usuall for God to give up the Rejectors of truth to vile affections and wicked lives <hi>(Rom.</hi> 1. 10. to the end, <hi>&amp; passim)</hi> I will add <hi>Grotius</hi> words on this Text, [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>ex operibus iniquitatis ut infra dicitur. c.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 23. <hi>Atqui dicat aliquis, jam dictum est pietatem ab istis vel maximè simulari: sane, sed verum est illud Mimi, Citò ad naturam ficta reciderunt suam.</hi> Lysias: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Interdum morâ aliquâ, interdum atttentione solâ opus est. Secerni, inquit</hi> Cicero, <hi>blandus amicus à vero, &amp; internosci tam potest adhibitâ diligentiâ, quàm omniafucata &amp; simulata à sinceris &amp; veris. Non diu proficient inquit</hi> Paulus <hi>nam insipientia illorum manifesta fiet. &amp;c. Fructus eorum hi esse solent, quod perpessiones de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugiunt, allectant eos qui in vitiis haerent, praesertìm opulentiores, questiones movent nihil facientes ad profectum pietatis, libenter obtrectant aliis, praesertìm in dignitate positis, ut</hi>
                  <pb n="400" facs="tcp:166114:17"/>
                  <hi>ea libertatis specie se apud populum jactent, &amp; ad istas res dogmata sua accommodant, ut videre est in utrâque ad Tim. in Jud. Epist. &amp; Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>atque ita ostendunt se tales esse quales revera sunt, fastuosos, odii &amp; invidentiae plenos, maledicos, avaros, neque tam ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enos à voluptatibus quàm existimari volunt, ut iisdem locis videre est. Quae siquis dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genter conferat cum iis quae de Corintho, deque Nicolao, aut si, &amp;c.]</hi> If you would have more proof of it, Mr. <hi>T.</hi> when a little came to himself, told you <hi>pag.</hi> 83. that it is [the course of many Souldiers and others, who against the denyal of able Teachers, to whom the teaching of the Gospel is committed, love to get into the Pulpits of the ablest men, to vent their peculiar conceits, and oft-times their pernicious errours, not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to preach to the ignorant the clear truths of faith and a holy life in places where they have no preacher, but to new Converts to pervert them, and draw them from their able Teachers, and to disquiet them and their Congregations, by frivolous exceptions.] I know very many of these men; but not one of many which are not Anabaptists. And the most of them (how ignorant soever) are boasters of themselves, and despisers of their Brethren: speaking in that language as Mr. <hi>T.</hi> doth, when he so vilifieth all the Ministers that were at the dispute (as that they weigh little with them that know them &amp;c.) when I think there were some as learned, and many as godly as himself; and give as good testimony of it by doctrine and life.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>T.</hi> will never prove, that by [sheeps cloathing] is not meant the fairness of their pretences, but their good lives.</p>
               <p>Sure he hath not read <hi>Hobsons</hi> Book, or else he durst not defend or so excuse it. And doth he not know how the Press doth spawn this kind of vermine so thick, that they are among us as the frogs and locusts in <hi>Egypt,</hi> overspreading the Land?</p>
               <p>For his offence at my forboding (as he calls it,) let him 1 cast his eye upon poor <hi>Wales,</hi> and remember the curse he past even now. 2 Review Mr. <hi>Bayly,</hi> and see whether he railed or prophesied.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>§. 22.</head>
               <p>The speech which Mr. <hi>T.</hi> is here blamed for, was uttered more then once in Pulpit and private speech. It was not <hi>de facto praeterito</hi> only, [that no one Country were discipled] nor of the manner only [that it was not done altogether] or [by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate.] But it was in answer to our argument from <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. which speaks <hi>de Debito,</hi> of the Ministerial Duty of Discipling Nations, and to what we say from the Prophesies that God will <hi>de futuro</hi> Disciple Nations: as if 1 It were not Ministers duty to endeavor the Discipling of any whole Nation (for then he must endeavour to Disciple Infants) nor a part of the work of that Commission. 2 Or that Christ would never accomplish it in this world, (when he hath promised it so oft; see my Addition, <hi>pag.</hi> 339, 340.) As for what he saith of <hi>Moses</hi> and Magistrates, if you peruse what I have said to that already, I think it will appear that he is no where more vertiginous then in this. He concludes with a [sleighting of my curse, <hi>pag.</hi> 217.] where I only desire the cure of his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, or if he proceed to publish errour, that it may not succeed; and this he calls [a curse.] It is but such a curse as I desire to my self, that the Lord would not suffer me to be an instrument of wronging his Church and Truth by my mistakes; or if I have done it ignorantly in this or any other writing, that he would forgive it, and shew me my error, and let me live to right the Church and Truth so wronged. This is my dayly prayer to God, especially as to those points where I find my dissent to my brethren so offensive. And the like forgiveness I desire of <hi>Mr. T.</hi> if I have any where un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advisedly or ignorantly wronged him: which I know my frail soul is so prone to that
<pb n="401" facs="tcp:166114:17"/> its most likely I have, though I should not see wherein; for I know my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature will shew it self in all that I do.) And I promise him if God shew me any weighty particulars of wrong, particularly to confess them. In the mean time I profess that the roughness which appears in my writings on this Subject, was provoked from the consideration of the Cause, and especially of the deep wound given to the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel by the Anabaptists of this age, and the attempts in hand; and the fearful danger that the Ministry and Churches of Christ are now in by reason of them; But when I think of my truly beloved Brother Mr. <hi>T.</hi> it not only grieves me that he is so deep in this Cause, but also that I am forced to speak so harshly to him, (which I knew would displease him) for his Causes sake. It hath cost me dearer to endeavour the Churches deliverance, and the rescuing of an endangered Ministry and Gospel, then it hath done Mr. <hi>T.</hi> And therefore let him not blame me, if I let not all go so patiently as some expect. If I so oft ventured my life against them that threatned these heretofore; let me be suffered to speak a sharp word or two against those that have brought them into as apparent hazzard; (except I be a stranger to, or utterly mistaken in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions of the present Agents and affairs,) I am certain, have brought our sacred Profession under greater obloquy and contempt. And let me adde (though I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make Mr. <hi>T.</hi> believe that I call him not a Heretick,) that I am so far from the violence and unpeaceableness that Mr. <hi>T.</hi> doth charge me with, that I am wholly of Mr. <hi>Marshals</hi> judgment (in his late Sermon for Unity) that men for Infant-baptism, and against it, should quietly and lovingly live together in the same Church. And I should tenderly love such as differ from me in this, and have communion with them, if they were of my charge: so be it when they have modestly given a reason of their judgment, (if called thereto) they would desist from further solliciting others to their way; (as I would do my self on the contrary side, if I were called to be a private Member of a Rebaptized Church, and Mr. <hi>T.</hi> were my Teacher.) But if they think they are bound to take all seasons and advantages, by secret sollicitations and publique disturbing contradictions, to propagate their opinions, and bring all others to them, as if Gods Glory lay upon their so doing, I know no way of having peace with such men, were the difference smaller then this of Infant-baptism; but I think all good Christians should avoid their Communion, as the fire-brands of the Church and enemies of its Peace, Unity, and Prosperity.</p>
               <p>It seems to me God ordered Mr. <hi>T.</hi> to translate <hi>Cyprians</hi> Epistle to the disgrace of his Cause with the Vulgar themselves. For none can be so blind as not to see in it the Antiquity of Infant-baptism, which is all that we urge it for. Only observe for the right understanding of it, that the objection that the Councel argues against, is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants incapacitie or uncleanness before the 8. day; and therefore the Arguments are only to the confutation of this, and not to give you the Grounds that warrant bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Infants; for those are supposed, the thing being unquestioned. Here was none that raised any doubt whether Infants should be baptized; but only whether before the eighth day.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>